Guide to Wendy Perron's "Concepts in Performance," In The Soho Weekly News 1976-1978 MSS 123
© 2009 Fales Library and Special Collections
Wendy Perron's "Concepts in Performance," In The Soho Weekly News (1976-78).
1976-1978
MSS 123
© 2009 Fales Library and Special Collections
0.5 Linear feet (1 box)
Perron wrote reviews for The Soho Weekly News and focused on a range of experimental performance practices that flourished in New York during the late 1970s. Being knowledgeable of the historical circumstances under which experimental "performance art" emerged in New York, She was among the earliest critics to write about this then new genre combining thick description and critical analysis. This collection is comprised of clippings of articles Perron wrote for The Soho Weekly News from 1976-1978.
Perron, Wendy
Provenance
Acquired through donation from Wendy Perron, New York in December 2001.
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival materials.
Historical/Biographical Note:
Wendy Perron is a teacher, writer and choreographer. She started her career as a choreographer and dancer in New York in the early 1970s. She was member of the Trisha Brown Company from 1975 to 1978 and danced for such choreographers as: Kenneth King, Rudy Perez, Sara Rudner, Twyla Tharp, among others. She formed and operated the Wendy Perron Dance Company from 1983 from 1994. Since the 1970's, She has taught various aspects of dance at Princeton, NYU, City College of New York, and Rutgers. In addition, she has been a frequent lecturer on the Judson Dance Theater of the 1960s. Perron has also written about dance for The New York Times, The Village Voice, and The Soho Weekly News. Recently, she has become the New York Editor of Dance Magazine, and is a Senior Fellow of the Vera List Center for Art & Politics at the New School University.
Sources:
"ACDFA Central Region Festival, Brief Biographies of Central Region Festival Faculty; Adjudicators." University of Iowa, College of Education. 3 Mar. 2002. [Online: http://www.uni.edu/coe/hpels/acdf/3rd/bio.htm1; Nov. 2002.].
Scope and Content Note
The Wendy Perron "Concepts in Performance" collection is a part of the Downtown Collection at the Fales Library, New York University. The Fales Library is the primary special collections division of the NYU libraries, housing nearly 200,000 volumes of English and American literature from 1700 to the present. Strengths of the collection include the development of the English and American novel, with an emphasis on the Gothic and the Victorian novel.
The Fales Library's collection of Wendy Perron's "Concepts in Performance" column, published in The Soho Weekly News, spans from 1976-1978. In her column, Perron reviews a range of experimental performance practices that flourished in New York during the late 1970s. Among these are Steve Paxton's Contact Improvisation, Laurie Anderson's sound performances involving electric violin, Trisha Brown's Accumulation pieces, and Merce Cunningham's integrations of dance, music, and theatre. Other artists and ensembles whose performances Perron reviews are John Cage, Lucinda Childs, Michael Kirby, Jackson Mac Low, Meredith Monk, Yvonne Rainer, Stuart Sherman, Squat Theatre, and Robert Wilson.
Perron's column is important for several reasons. First, she is among the earliest critics to write about a new genre known as "Performance Art." In the 1970s, "Performance Art" came to designate experimental forms of embodied expression that fell outside the conventional categories of theatre, dance, or music. Secondly, Perron combines thick description and critical analysis. This combination not only allows readers to visualize the performances that occurred, but also sheds light on the aesthetic, political, and theoretical issues underlying a given piece. Thirdly, Perron is knowledgeable about the historical circumstances under which performance art emerged in New York, she is thus able to identify the central characteristics informing performance art of the 1970s, distinguishing it from 1960s experimental theatre.
Arrangement
Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
The files are grouped into one series.
Folder 1: Miscellaneous Originals (1976-1978)
Folder 2: Copies (1976-1978)
Folder 3: Perron, Wendy: Articles, 1976 (Originals)
Folder 4: Perron, Wendy: Articles, 1976 (Duplicates)
Folder 5: Perron, Wendy: Articles, 1977 (Originals)
Folder 6: Perron, Wendy: Articles, 1977 (Duplicates)
Folder 7: Perron, Wendy: Articles, 1978 (Originals)
Folder 8: Perron, Wendy: Articles, 1977 (Duplicates)
Related Material at the Fales Library and Special Collections
Please see the Judson Memorial Church Archive for related materials pertaining to Performance Art of the 1960s and 1970s. The Judson Memorial Church was a theatrical 'home base' for many (though by no means all) of the performance artists and ensembles whose work Perron reviews in her column.
The Judson Memorial Church Archive
The Robert Alexander Papers
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Perron, Wendy; Soho Weekly News.;; Choreography --United States.; Choreography--History--20th century.; Clippings.; Dance criticism.; Dance--New York (State)--New York--Reviews.; New York (N.Y.); Performance art--New York (State)--New York.; Reviews.; Theater -- New York (State) -- New York -- Reviews.
- Folder 1: Miscellaneous Originals (1976-1978).
  - Grow Up or Shut Up or Tell Me Something New, by Robert Patrick, October 6th, 1977. (Folder 1, Object 1)
  - Exclusive, Never-Before-Published in the History of Man Interview with Sigmund Freud, by Lewis Grossberger, October 6th, 1977. (Folder 1, Object 2)
  - Reading For Fun and Art's Profit, by Wendy Perron, no date given., undated (Folder 1, Object 3)
  - Deep Breathing Accordion, by Wendy Perron, no date given., undated (Folder 1, Object 4)
- Folder 2: Copies (1976-1978).
  - Miscellaneous Copies; All items in this folder are duplicates of the materials listed above; the contents are identical to that of Folder 1., 1976-1978 (Folder 2)
- Folder 3: Perron, Wendy: Articles, 1976 (Originals).
  - Finding a Thread in a Haystack, reviews by Wendy Perron and others, January 22nd, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 1)
  - Of Baggage, Short Stories, and Reflections, reviews by Wendy Perron and others, January 29th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 2)
  - Followable Dancing, review of Mary Overlie and David Gordon by Wendy Perron, March 4th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 3)
  - Energy Sparks, review of Wendy Rogers by Wendy Perron, March 11th, 1976. "Performance Diary," by Peter Frank, April 1st, 1976 (incomplete article). (Folder 3, Object 4)
  - Unadorned, review of Suzanne Harris by Wendy Perron, April 8th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 5)
  - People Improvisation, review of Grand Union by Wendy Perron, May 6th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 6)
  - New Dimensions in Self-Consciousness, review of Michael McClard by Wendy Perron, May 20th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 7)
  - Small Night Music in a Fog, Review of Yoshimasa Wada by Peter Zummo, May 27th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 8)
  - Undiscovered: Bill Horowitz, review of Bill Horowitz by Wendy Perron, May 27th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 9)
  - Keeping in Line, review of Philip Glass, Dickie Landry, Andy DeGroat by Sally Banes, June 3rd, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 10)
  - The Ceremony of Leonard Crow Dog, reviews of Leonard Crow Dog, June 10th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 11)
  - Unpremeditated Honesty, review by Wendy Perron, June 10th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 12)
  - Consuming Determination, review of Lucinda Childs by Wendy Perron, June 17th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 13)
  - It All Depends on How You Define It, review of Wendy Perron by Robert J. Pierce, June 17th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 14)
  - Death or Rebirth, review of Julie Hymen by Mark Savitt, July 1st, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 15)
  - Discovery, review of Tony Azito by Wendy Perron, July 1st, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 16)
  - Letters, response by John Malpede to Perron's June 10th review, July 1st, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 17)
  - When Is a Recital Not? review of U.S. Terpsichore by Robert J. Pierce, July 8th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 18)
  - Secret Life of Cities Surrealistic Baedekers, Review of Meredith Monk and Ping Chong, July 8th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 19)
  - Downtown Exiles, review of Tony Kushner, et al. by Stephanie Woodward, September 30th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 20)
  - Live and Non-Live; Motion and Stillness, review of Sylvia Whitman by Wendy Perron, Nov. 25th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 21)
  - "Three Angles on a Three Part Structure, review of Michael Kirby by Wendy Perron, Dec. 2nd, 1976. 23. Roots and Rituals,"" review of Geoff Hendricks by Sally Banes, December 9th, 1976." (Folder 3, Object 22)
  - Backworks, review of Barbara Moore and Jon Hendricks by Wendy Perron, Dec. 9th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 24)
  - Older is Better, review of Merce Cunningham by Wendy Perron, December 16th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 25)
  - Transmission From Space, Review of Earth, Moon, Mars, and Jupiter by Peter Zummo, Dec. 23rd, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 26)
  - "Exporting SoHo," by Wendy Perron, December 30th, 1976. (Folder 3, Object 27)
- Folder 4: Perron, Wendy: Articles, 1976 (Duplicates).
  - Perron, Wendy: Articles, 1976 (Duplicates). All items in this folder are duplicates of the materials listed above; the contents are identical to that of Folder 3. (Folder 4)
- Folder 5: Perron, Wendy: Articles, 1977 (Originals).
  - Improvisation Part I: The Man Who Gets Away With It, review by Wendy Perron, January 6th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 1)
  - Improvisation Part II: Acquaintanceship, review by Wendy Perron, January 13th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 2)
  - "Knife's Edge," review of Beth Soll by Wendy Perron, January 20th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 3)
  - Politics as Analysis, review of Lee Breuer by Madeleine Burnside, January 20th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 4)
  - Going to Pieces, review by Stephanie Woodward, January 27th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 5)
  - Lost In Translation: The Americanization of Jewish Humor, by Wendy Perron, February 3rd, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 6)
  - David Behrman, John Cage, Merce Cunningham, review by Peter Zummo, February 3rd, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 7)
  - Bad Taste, review of Now I Know Why Cannibals Eat Their Enemies by Sally Banes, Feb. 10th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 8)
  - Reading Writing, review of women writers by Wendy Perron, February 17th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 9)
  - Haystack, review of performance art by Wendy Perron, February 24th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 10)
  - Words That Work, review of Robert Barry by Wendy Perron, March 3, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 11)
  - When the Wind if High, review of Trisha Brown by Stephanie Woodward, March 10th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 12)
  - Inner Vision Outer Space, review of Nancy Topf by Stephanie Woodward, March 17th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 13)
  - Chosen Toil, review of Steve Paxton by Stephanie Woodward, March 24th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 14)
  - Works With Words, review of Lawrence Kucharz by Peter Zummo, March 31st, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 15)
  - Looking the Other Way, review of James Barth by Wendy Perron, April 7th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 16)
  - Half Hazard, by Wendy Perron, April 14th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 17)
  - Elemental Sounds, review of Alvin Lucier by Peter Zummo, April 28th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 18)
  - Black Holes at Large, review of Star Station by Wendy Perron, April 28th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 19)
  - Nursery Rhymes, review of Julia Heyward and Paula Longendyke, May 5th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 20)
  - New Mysteries, review of The Venue Caft Byrd Hoffman Studio, June 2nd, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 21)
  - Kushner Bares All, review of Robert Kushner by Wendy Perron, June 9th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 22)
  - Guesswork, review of Meredith Monk by Wendy Perron, June 16th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 23)
  - A Rhythmical Guy, review of Dave Van Tieghem by Stephanie Woodward, June 23rd, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 24)
  - Only an Illusion, review of street performance by Wendy Perron, July 14th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 25)
  - Cuba, New York, review of New Cuban Cinema by Stephanie Woodward, July 21st, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 26)
  - Direct to the Heart, review of the Big Apple Circus by Stephanie Woodward, July 28th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 27)
  - Starting From Nothing, review of Michael Moschen by Wendy Perron, September 22nd, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 28)
  - That's Entertainment, review of Becky Arnold by Sally Banes, October 13th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 29)
  - Fearless Squatters, review of Squat Theatre's Pig, Child, Fire by Wendy Perron, October 20th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 30)
  - Poor White Tails, review of Tony Azito by Wendy Perron, November 10th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 31)
  - New Morning, review of Tall Tree by Wendy Perron, November 24th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 32)
  - "Susan Sontag: On Writing, Art, Feminism, Life and Death," interview by Wendy Perron, December 1st, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 33)
  - Voices of Many Voices, review of Julia Heyward and Pooh Kaye by Wendy Perron, December 15th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 34)
  - Cage's Shell Game, review of John Cage by Wendy Perron, December 29th, 1977. (Folder 5, Object 35)
- Folder 6: Perron, Wendy: Articles, 1977 (Duplicates).
  - Perron, Wendy: Articles, 1977 (Duplicates). All items in this folder are duplicates of the materials listed above; the contents are identical to that of Folder 5., undated (Folder 6)
- Folder 7: Perron, Wendy: Articles, 1978 (Originals).
  - 45 Minutes, Spent With Friends, review of Wendy Perron and Susan Rethorst, by Robert J. Pierce, Jan. 19th, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 1)
  - Within You/Without You, review of Robert Ashley by Sally Banes, January 19th, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 2)
  - Historical Immaterialism, review of Ann Wilson's Butler's Lives of the Saints, by Sally Banes, January 26th, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 3)
  - Two-Track Mind, review of Amy Taubin by Wendy Perron, January 26th, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 4)
  - Failure: An Exhibition, Preview of Bill Lundberg by Jane Dubose Jones, February 2nd, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 5)
  - Gallery Humor, review of Michael Smith by Noel Carroll, February 2nd, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 6)
  - "Austerity and Oppression," review of Worksong by Wendy Perron, February 23rd, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 7)
  - Poet in the Bathroom, Review of Barbara Kruger by Louise Steinman, February 23rd, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 8)
  - "Dummy Duality," review of Charles Ludlam's The Ventriloquist's Wife by Eileen Blumenthal, Feb. 23rd, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 9)
  - Engineering Images, review of Sylvia Whitman by Sally Banes, March 16th, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 10)
  - Spring Mumbo-Jumbo, review of Anna Halprin by Sally Banes, March 23rd, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 11)
  - "Humor, Blood, and Guts," review of Lanny Harrison by Wendy Perron, March 30th, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 12)
  - Lovely Lifelessness, review of Love of Life Orchestra by Wendy Perron, April 20th, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 13)
  - Adored, review of The Children of Theatre Street by Wendy Perron, May 1st, 1978 (incomplete article). (Folder 7, Object 14)
  - "On the Rocks," review of Pooh Kaye by Wendy Perron, May 4th, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 15)
  - The End of the Trail, Review of Echo Ranch by Noel Carroll, May 11th, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 16)
  - Flu as Fashion and Art as Business, review of Richard Foreman's Fashion Show by Sally Banes, May 18th, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 17)
  - A Promising Journeyman, review of Hard Pore Corn by Noel Carroll, May 18th, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 18)
  - Dancing Working, review of Miner's Lamp Dance Group by Wendy Perron, May 25th, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 19)
  - Sweet, review of Short and Suite by Sally R. Sommer and Erica Sommer, June 1st, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 20)
  - Celebrating Survival, review by Sally Banes, June 15th, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 21)
  - P.S. Afterthoughts, review of Patti Smith by Wendy Perron, June 15th, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 22)
  - N Structures, No Cages, review of Simone Forti and Peter Van Riper by Wendy Perron, August 31st, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 23)
  - Tout Sweet, review of Andy deGroat and Dancers by Sally Banes, August 31st, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 24)
  - Paxton Untitled, review of Steve Paxton by Yvonne Rainer, November 16th, 1978. (Folder 7, Object 25)
- Folder 8: Perron, Wendy: Articles, 1977 (Duplicates).
  - Perron, Wendy: Articles, 1977 (Duplicates). All items in this folder are duplicates of the materials listed above; the contents are identical to that of Folder 7 (Folder 8)